[Music]
Stanford
University the goal tonight is not to
tell you why the higs B arm is the best
thing since flush toilets you've read
all of that anybody who here has
probably read all of the
um the hype the
uh excited
breathless uh superlatives that uh that
have the newspapers and so
forth things B arm is going to explain
the origin of the universe and this and
that I'm not going to do
that first of all before I say it the
the excitement and the enthusiasm is
Justified it's not that it's not
justified it is
Justified uh the history is fantastic
it's an unbelievable event and so forth
but that's not what my thing is it's not
what I do well what I do well is explain
how things work my goal tonight is going
to show it be to show you as so far as I
can in one hour which is tough which is
hard and it may not work but as well as
I can to explain to you the nuts and
bolts of what higs physics is
about one of my closest friends
incidentally is is named franois laare
and Fran glair would be appalled if you
knew that I was standing here talking
about the kids effect since Fran onir
was the discoverer of it so from time to
time they may call it the brout onir
higs effect but I also May slip and
slide and just call it the effect
because I tend to get like everybody
else uh all right so how it
works first of all
there's a lot of moving Parts a lot of
pieces that I would have to that I would
have to explain to you
first uh to really do it right and I'm
going to try to explain those pieces in
little in little modules should we say
it's a highly quantum mechanical
effect it cannot really be understood
without quantum
mechanics and so I would begin with a
course in quantum mechanics and let's
say the course in quantum mechanics
consists of just one thing things are
quantized quantized means that they come
in discrete integer
quantities the most famous example of
this is angular momentum angular
momentum the rotational Properties or
the rotational momentum of an object are
quantized which means they come come in
discrete steps and the discrete steps
are one plunk unit one unit of plants
constant we'll take that as all we
really need to know about for the most
part about quantum mechanics
tonight the next concept which is an
easier one at least I think it's an
easier one it's a classical concept is
the idea of a field a field is just a
condition in space it could be the
electric field it could be the magnetic
field it could be a gravitational field
whatever you think of is being present
in space which
characterizes the conf the behavior of
space at that instant and in that place
in uh in space in time so field space
can be filled with
Fields now ordinarily you imagine in
empty space empty space is the thing we
call a vacuum from a quantum mechanics
point of view the vacuum is just a state
of lowest energy nothing there no
energy other than what quantum mechanics
requires there to be
there and so you ordinarily think that
the fields that could inhabit space are
zero in empty space the electric field
the magnetic field and so forth but
there's no important requirement of
physics that says that that should be
the case let's imagine a world filled
with electric
field how could that electric field get
there well it might be there because
there are capacitor plates infinitely
far away so far away we can't tell
they're
there there we would have a world in
which there was an electric field it
would just be there empty space would
have an electric
field now when you think about Fields oh
we're beginning a little bit too early
okay you're going to
wait all right so what I was saying to
the audience two things the first was
that quantum mechanics were going to
summarize by one simple statement that
things are quantized in quantum
mechanics quantized means they come in
discrete bits the most important example
is angular momentum not the most
important necessarily the most important
example but the most important um
example for me tonight will be angular
momentum and angular momentum is has to
do with rotating objects and so forth
angular momentum in quantum mechanics
unlike classical mechanics comes in
discrete units the unit is Plank's
constant you can't have a tenth of a
unit of angular momentum you can only
have angular momentum 0 1 2 3 -1 -2
-3 you can also have half integers but
we're not going to worry about that
tonight but no you can't have angular
momentum Pi only discrete integers
that's the first uh fact that I want you
to
remember the other fact from quantum
mechanics that we'll have to remember
also is the uncertainty principle that
we come to it now the other thing we
spoke about was Fields fields are things
that can fill space electric field
magnetic field gravitational field other
kinds of fields that exist in
physics they are
functions of space they can vary from
place to
place and they affect for example the
way things move an example would be an
electric field affecting the way a
Charged particle
moves now the other thing I said was you
can imagine a
world in which for all practical
purposes empty space is filled with a
field an example would be if I went out
to Alpha centuri at that
end and excuse me I don't know what's
out
there excuse
me yeah whatever's out there and place
some capacitor
plates big capacitor plate out there big
one out there make an electric field in
between they're so far apart that we
can't see them we would say that the
world is a world that exists with a
magnetic
field and we would say that charged
particles move in Peculiar ways but that
was just a fact of
nature
um generally speaking Fields cost
energy space without an electric field
has zero energy with an electric field
it has energy and if we were to PL not
the energy of a field a typical field
could be electric could be a magnetic
could be something
else generally we imagine that the field
energy as a function of the field
horizontally imagine the value of a
field vertically its
energy zero field right here and we
imagine exciting the field causing it to
vibrate causing it to vibrate by giving
it a push some region of space and
nearby the field will vibrate those
vibrations are quanta of the field they
are particles they are particles the
quanta of vibration of a field of
particles now you might have a situation
where there is more than one field
relevant let's call it fi and F prime or
whatever you want to call it doesn't
matter then instead of plotting the
field as one dimension
we might plot it as two-dimensional now
this is not space this is the value of
some collection of fields and then the
energy would depend on both Fields
here's an
example an energy function which looks
like that which simply says that no
matter how you displace the
field it costs
energy now
imagine that
this upside down paraboloid or whatever
it is was nice and symmetric nice and
rotationally symmetric in the field
space exactly like the top of my hat
here which as you can see is
symmetric and so the field as a oh yes
where's my little that's that's it right
the field as a function of position
would most likely if the energy is as
low as possible just sit at the bottom
of the potential energy of the field
just to lower the energy as much as
possible so we might think of the field
at every point in space a little ball
which can be made to oscillate Back in
Forth and do things and those are just
oscillations of the behavior of physics
in a local region of space as I said
they often correspond the quantum
particles those oscillations but for the
moment they're just
oscillations now one of the things we
could do if we had a field whose values
were like the position in the Hat here
would be to start it out displaced from
the origin let's say up to here and then
start it
moving in a
circle just in the same way you could
take this ball and if it was if the Hat
was really nice and smooth and symmetric
give it a push and it would go around in
a in a circle
that circular motion of the field is
very very similar in a way to angular
momentum it's not angular momentum in
space but it's a kind of angular
momentum that exists in the field
space that angular momentum like all
angular momenta are quantized come in
integer multiples of Plank's constant
what do they correspond to they
correspond to something else that is
also quantized in nature the value for
example of el
charge so in modern physics the way one
thinks about the electric charge in a
region is that in some region of space a
particle a Charged particle a Charged
particle is viewed as an excitation of
the field in which the field is made to
spin
around in the internal space of the
field not in real space but in the
internal space of the
field that's one way in fact it's the
main way that we think about without
charge as a kind of rotation in an
internal
space okay now what I want you to do is
Imagine taking the hat and turning it
over imagine that the potential energy
was not turn it over this way excuse me
this way is the way that the potential
energy is minimum at the crown of the
hat but if the potential energy really
looked like that so that it was Max imum
at the top of the Hat then the top of
the hat would not be a position of
equilibrium it would be a position of
unstable equilibrium it would look like
this turning over the Hat the crown of
the Hat
now this is the way you know the real
hat looks like this and it doesn't uh
okay let's just let's make the um
how's that that look like a hat
yeah looks like a hat what kind of hat
does it look like to
you looks like a Soma right looks like a
Mexican hat physicists call this kind of
potential energy function a Mexican hat
believe it or not it's called a Mexican
hat it turns back up the top is
unstable if a PO a ball was put at the
top it would roll down and where would
it go it would go to the brim of the
hat if for some reason the potential
energy of a field was like this then the
state of lowest energy would not be at
zero field it would be out
here now that's kind of interesting it
would be a vacuum a world which had a
field just like having an electric field
except it's not an electric field in
which the value of the field at every
point in space was not zero you might
notice it how would you notice it well
you might notice it because it might
affect other things and indeed it does
affect other things as we will
see but there's now something
interesting you can do that you couldn't
do here over here if you wanted to set
this thing into rotation you would have
to displace the field a little bit
because it doesn't mean anything to
rotate right at the center if you wanted
to set up a rotation you displace the
field and then give it a flip so making
a Charged particle costs some
energy
here you can imagine setting this thing
into rotation with just a little flick
that costs no energy it costs no energy
because you don't have to ride up the
side of the
Hat other words you could have a motion
in which I'm not
got it you got it you got it you
understand right you got to have a
motion in which that field slowly wound
around the top of the potential in fact
it could do it everywhere simultaneously
not in real space but in this field
space that would correspond again to a
charge if rotation in this internal
space corresponds to some kind of charge
but now the whole world if the whole
field was moving like that would have a
little bit of charge in it a charge
density charge filling
space and essentially no cost of
energy that phenomenon is called
a condensate it's called spontaneous
symmetry braking but it's also called a
condensate a condensate in space of
charge now you might say okay look I
want to find the lowest energy that the
vacuum can have that empty space can
have my best bet is to make the field
not move with time just like a ball at
the bottom of the sombrero hat here
there's also kinetic energy of motion
causing the field to move around in a
circle like that would cost some energy
so you would say the true lowest energy
state of the world should be with a
field either here or here or here it
could be anywhere along the the rim of
the hat but it should be standing still
right the problem with no angular
momentum or no charge empty space should
not have charge the problem with that is
the uncertainty
principle let me remind you what the
uncertainty principle
says it says that if you have a
object and you're interested in its
position X in ordinary space now and its
momentum P velocity if you like the
uncertainty principle says that the
uncertainty in its position times the
uncertainty in the momentum is greater
than or equal to
what plunks
constant you can't have something both
standing still and having zero momentum
if it's stand sorry you can't have
something standing still namely no
momentum and also localize at a point
Delta P * Delta X is greater than H bar
same thing here if you know where the
field is on this Mexican hat if you know
with great Precision then it follows
from the uncertainty principle that it
must have a very large uncertainty in
how fast it's moving around here Ah
that's interesting now that would say
that you can't have empty space with no
charge in it can't have empty space with
no charge in it because if you lay the
field down at this point you know where
it is on the rim of the hat and if you
know where it is there's a necessary
uncertainty in the charge the charge
being like the angular momentum all
right so where are we then if this were
the case for electric charge for
ordinary electric charge we would say
that the vacuum empty space Not only is
filled with charges in a certain sense
but a totally uncertain amount of charge
totally uncertain and this is a Quantum
effect a totally un certain amount of
charge there would be equal probability
let's take a little volume of space
there would be equal probability that
the charge was
zero or that the charge was one or minus
one or two or minus two 3 minus three
now this is truly odd this is not
something you should try to visualize
because you can't visualize an uncertain
amount of charge but nevertheless that
is what a region of space would look
like if you measured its charge it could
be anything from minus infinity to plus
infinity okay now I want you to imagine
that you have an extra charged
particle an extra charged particle and
you throw it in you don't know initially
what the charge is but what does that do
it displaces the charge by one unit
let's suppose it was a positive charge
you've displac the charge by one unit
and so if it was zero to begin with it's
now one if it was one to begin with it's
now two if it was two to begin with it's
three if it was minus one it's 0o 1 -
one min-2 and so forth but that's
exactly the same as what we started with
we started with something which had an
uncertain amount of
charge equally likely for any value of
charge and what did we end up with after
we threw the charge in exactly the same
thing what if we pluck the charge out of
this
thing same thing so a condensate is a
funny configuration of
space where with respect to whatever
kind of charge we're talking about it's
so uncertain that you wouldn't even
realize it if you put an extra one in or
pulled one
out now the real world is not like that
with respect to electric charge we know
if we have a charge in space so it's not
like that with respect to electric
charge however there are materials that
behave like this
superconductors superconductors are
exactly like
this so it's not unheard of it's not a
totally new thing to have a condensate
of charge where in a region the charge
is completely uncertain
okay that was module number one if you
like condensates or what is sometimes
called the spontaneous breaking of
symmetry module number two the standard
model now we come to particle
physics and I'll give you a short course
in particle physics first of all
particles have mass and the mass can be
anywhere from
zero we're talking about small particles
now we're not talking about railroad
engines or uh or Stars we're talking
about small
particles we call them Elementary
particles but there's also a maximum
Mass they can have if they were bigger
than that they would form a black hole
if they were more massive than that if a
point particle was more massive than
something it would form a black hole and
it would be something different so up to
some Maximum and that maximum is called
the plunk Mass it is not a very large
Mass it's neither a very large mass nor
a very small Mass it happens to be about
100,000th of a gram a small dust mode
but that is the heaviest that a Char
that a um that an elementary particle
can be without turning into a black hole
and if you ask now where on this chart
from zero this is called
mlan up to the maximum where are the
ordinary particles the electrons the
photons the um quarks
they are way way down
here the largest mass of a known
elementary particle is about
10-7 of the plunk Mass why are the
particles so light well one answer is in
order to detect massive particles you
have to have a lot of energy in order to
have a lot of energy you need a big
accelerator we've only made accelerators
up to some uh size and so for all we
know the rest of this is filled with
particles and that's probably true
that's probably true but what is special
about these particles well first of all
let me name them and then I'll tell you
what's special about them that makes
them Clump up at zero Mass let's name
them the particles of the standard model
they come in two varities it is not
important that you know the difference
well I'll give you a rough idea of what
the difference is they come in two
varieties called
firion and
bosons the firmians are all the
particles that make up matter in the
usual sense the electron which I'll just
call E well the neutrino goes along with
the electron that's a new the electron
the neutrino
quirks there's a variety of different
quirks incidentally there are several
different kinds of electrons we call
them electron mu on tow it doesn't
matter but they're very electron likee
and several kinds of
neutrinos the electrons have the
electric charge the neutrinos don't and
then there are quarks a variety of
different kinds of quarks up quarks down
quarks this kind of Quark that kind of
quark and those quarks several different
kinds of quarks you know what the role
of them are they make up the
proton and uh that's about it for um for
Fons for bosons on the other hand and
there first of all a photon gamma gamma
for a gamma ray Photon there's an object
called the gluon G it's very much like a
photon it's very much like a photon but
it doesn't have anything to do with
atoms it has to do with nuclei and
protons and neutrons it plays the same
role in holding the nucleus or better
yet the proton together as the photon
plays in creating electrical fields
inside an atom so there's the
gluon and then there are two others
called W
bosons and
Zebo for the most part we won't be
interested in any of them except the
photon here and there but mostly we'll
be interested in the Zebo
Zone that's it that's the standard model
that's all there is to it with one
exception I've left something out it's a
thing you came to find out about tonight
okay so will come to it if there was no
Expos on then this would be it now what
is special about this set of particles
what's special about them is for reasons
that I'm going to come to reasons that I
will come to all of these particles in
the standard model as I've laid it out
here with nothing else in it would all
have mass equal to zero they would be
massless and explain why that is in a
little
while we often hear that it's the role
of the higs bosan to create mass for
particles or to give the particles their
Mass that's the expression that I've
heard over and over the higs gives
particles why do why do the particles
have to be given
Mass why can't they have mass of their
own why do they have to be given Mass
well as it turns out for reasons we'll
explain this set of particles is exact
the set of particles which would have no
Mass if this was all there was now in
part that explains in part it explains
why the particles why these particles
are so very light it's because they're
massless they have no Mass well not
quite we can't live with that because we
know that particles really do have
mass next question I'm going to draw
some figures over here what do these
particles do what kind of processes that
they are they involved in all right the
basic process of the standard
model this is an over simplification but
it's qualitatively right is that the
firion there's a firon moving along and
I will describe a firon by a solid line
solid because it's what makes up stuff
solid
line that's moving from one point in
SpaceTime to another point of space time
what the standard model does is it
causes the emission of
bosons a electron moving along can emit
a
photon electron moving along can emit a
photon and that's connected with the
electric
charge any electrically charged particle
can emit a
photon a photon that's the first thing
that the standard model does now this of
course is just Quantum
electrodynamics it does not have could
be the electron it could be any
electrically charged
particle
next The
Quirk let's see do we have room here
yeah we'll just do it the
Quark Quark let's just call it Q The
Quirk can emit a
gluon precisely the same pattern The
Quirk emits a gluon now the Quark can
also emit a photon if it happens to be
electrically charged and quarks are
electrically charged but electrons
cannot emit gluons gluons are the things
that bind quirks together to hold them
together into protons and
neutrons and then there's one more
important process for me tonight there
are two more processes but I'll just
write down one here and it
is either an electron oh incidentally a
neutrino cannot emit a photon it has no
electric
charge it cannot emit a gluon it's not a
quark
okay both electrons and
neutrinos and quirks for that matter can
emit the Zebo on where's the Zebo on
here's the Zebo on right here and when
they do
so the Zebo on being electrically
neutral the electric charge of whatever
is here doesn't
change so this is another process that
the standard model
describes now first of all why are the
Bon's
massless well the photon's massless we
know that it travels with a speed of
light now could we make a theory in
which the photon had some Mass yes we
could but the more important thing is
that we can make a theory in which the
photon doesn't have a mass why because
the photon doesn't have a
mass using the same kind of theory
the ZB Boon would not have a mass and
the gluon would not have a mass
everything would be
massless these would be the processes
that could happen these would be the
particles they would all be
massless okay now how do Fields how do
Fields give particles mass or better yet
more simply a simple example I'm going
to show you a simple example now the
simple example is how a field can affect
the mass of a particle we'll come back
in a moment to how it can give something
which didn't have mass mass but let's
take a more modest question how may
Fields affect the mass or better yet how
might they make different masses for
different particles so I'm going to show
you an
example this example is a little bit
contrived but it's a real
example a water molecule
water molecules have the basic property
that they're little dumbbells they have
a plus end and a minus end electrically
charge plus end and minus end uh they're
actually not they're more like y's you
know y with three ends but we can think
of them as having a plus end dumbbells
and a minus
end now the mass of a water molecule
water molecules have mass the mass of a
water molecule doesn't depend on its
orientation if we turned it over and
made a water molecule with its minus end
here and the plus end here it would have
exactly the same mass why it's the
symmetry of space space is the same in
every direction and so by
symmetry we would say that the water
molecule standing up straight has
exactly the same mass as the water
molecule standing on its head let's not
worry for tonight about whether it's
lying on its side
quantum mechanics tells us we don't have
to worry about anything but standing up
straight and lying on its head all right
so that's uh that's true about water
molecules their mass is the same if
they're standing up straight and think
of water molecules now as particles
think of them just as particles we don't
know what they are they're just little
Elementary particles we can't see them
and so we have two kinds of particles
the upstanding and a standing on his
head particle with exactly the same
mass now I thought I had a
purple no purple I told them to put
purple I'll have to use orange
where over
here underneath the board you mean under
here
oh
good all right I have my color coding in
my notes here and if I blow it I'll be
terrible Okay so that looks Brown to
me it is brown okay let's create a
region in which there's an electric
field we're going to make a field it
could be between two capacitor plates
the capacitor plates could be far apart
it doesn't matter but let's put them the
capacitor plates here and here and
inside that region let's create an
electric
field the electric field in this case
pointing up that means it pushes plus
charges up and minus charges down if I
have my signs
right and let's take one of these water
molecules and insert it in
here once I insert the water molecule in
here the energy of the upstanding water
molecule and the upside down water
molecule are
different which one has less energy the
one with the plus up has less energy and
the one turn turned over has larger
energy the water molecule itself is
electrically neutral it has no electric
charge but it's a little dipole it has a
pair of charges and which one has more
energy depends on the sign of the
electric
field okay so there we are we have two
water molecules two types of water
molecules two different particles we
could give them different names we could
call it water and um uh
scotch and the water molecule has one
one energy the scotch molecule has
another uh energy and there they are
well by e equal
mc² this also tells us that the two
molecules have different mass now in
practice this would be a tiny different
Mass between them but they would have
different Mass so the same effect of
this field which exerts itself on
charged particles does something to
neutral water molecules incidentally
notice that it doesn't exert any net
force on the water molecule the water
molecule moves smoothly through it with
no Force no net force acting on it but
there was a difference in the up uh in
the uh two configurations of the water
molecule and so it's as if we had
particles of two different Mass so this
is just an example of how a field
creates mass in this case it increases
one mass and decreases the other
Mass incidentally if you read some of
the literature and they'll tell you
about how the um Hig field gives a mass
I've read any number of places that it's
something like space being filled with
molasses it is not like space being
filled with molasses the vacuum is not
sticky and one of the things that
molasses would do well the the idea is
that massive particles move slower than
massless particles so the idea is that
molasses slows them down but Fields
don't slow particles down if you give
the particle a push in this direction it
will just continue to move because
there's no net force on it it'll just
slide right through this
thing
frictionlessly no uh no impedance no uh
no friction no molasses there's not the
other the other analogy I once heard is
um that it was like trying to push a
snow plow through a heavy snow in the
Arctic uh it's got nothing to do with it
whatever that's a that's a that's a lazy
way to explain it and it's a wrong way
to explain
it okay so there we are but now let's
think of this in a slightly different
way the electric field in here
can also be pictured in terms of
photons a field is another way of
talking about a collection a condensate
of photons an electric field we can
replace the electric
field
by a condensate the same kind of
condensate the same kind of condensate
of photons Let's uh draw photons by just
a little squiggly lines fill this up
with photons how does it know which way
the electric field is pointing well
photons have a polarization they could
be up or they could be down so just
imagine this thing being filled with
photons but not filled in the usual way
but filled in a condensate what does a
condensate mean a condensate means that
if I pull one out it doesn't make any
difference if I put an extra one in it
doesn't make any difference that's the
meaning of the condensate so it's an
indefinite number of photons that's what
a field is indefinite and if you pull
one out nothing happens and now let's
reintroduce the
um the water molecule let's just draw
the water molecule moving through here
now I'm going to make the water molecule
red I've already blown my uh my color
coding here's a water molecule moving
through here and what is it going to do
it has charged particles inside it the
charged particles can Emit and absorb
photons they Emit and absorb photons
we've made the photons green now so it
emits photons but when it emits a photon
putting an extra Photon in doesn't
matter and so we usually draw that by
just putting a cross at the end a cross
simply means that throwing an extra
Photon in doesn't affect
anything photon is emitted and just is
absorbed or is
just um disappears into the
condensate as this object the dumbbell
moves through the electric field it's
constantly emitting and
absorbing these photons which get lost
in the condensate that is another way of
talking about how the field affects the
particle and depending on whether the
photons are polarized up or down this
effect of constantly being
absorbing and emitting photons will have
the effect of Shifting the energy of the
two configurations of the uh of the
dumbell that's simply an example of how
a
field can affect the mass of a particle
and how it can be thought of in terms of
particles and
condensates that's what I want you to
keep in
mind that
picture okay now come to Elementary
particles not dumbbells not
molecules first question is there any
reason why a particle or an object just
can't have a mass does it need an excuse
to have a mass uh does it need anything
called the higs phenomena to have a mass
well there are lots of things in nature
that have mass and have nothing whatever
to do with the higs phenomena let me
give you an
example imagine you had a box and let's
make that box at out of extremely light
stuff the lightest stuff you can think
of but it's a box with good reflecting
walls and fill it with lots of high
energy radiation bouncing off the walls
but never getting
out it's made out of massless stuff the
photons are massless they have no Mass
the Box we're imagining is made out of
stuff which is exceedingly light doesn't
have much
mass but there's plenty of energy in
there
lots and lots of energy well e equal
mc² and so this box will behave exactly
as if it had a mass we didn't need
anything to give Mass Just Energy that's
all it took are there any particles
which are like this which get Mass
having nothing to do with uh higs or
anything else yes the
proton the proton is a particle which is
made out of quarks quarks three quarks
and a bunch of gluons
G's a bunch of gluons a large number of
gluons quarks and gluons in the standard
model are
massless does that mean that the proton
would be massless if the quarks and
gluons were massless not at all if the
quarks and gluons were massless the
effect on the proton would be about a 1%
or even less change in its mass not much
at all where does its mass come from it
comes from the kinetic energy of these
massless particles rattling around in a
box the Box being created by the proton
so Mass doesn't have to come from black
holes are another example black holes
have mass it doesn't come from the higs
phenomenon doesn't have anything to do
with
higs so what is it about
the models of the St the particles of
the standard model which require us to
introduce a new ingredient all right so
I'm going to concentrate on the electron
let's concentrate on the
electron we don't need all of
this and what I need to tell you
about is the direct theory of
electrons but really we don't have to
know very much about the direct Theory
all we have to know is that electrons
have in and furthermore if an electron
was moving very fast down the axis here
let's say with close to the speed of
light we really accelerate that electron
then there's two possibilities the spin
of the electron can be right-handed like
that think of my thumb as the direction
of motion of the electron it can be
going that way like my right hand or it
can be going that way like my left hand
oh I didn't realize I could do that
now two kinds of electrons right-handed
and
left-handed okay now do right-handed
electrons always stay right-handed can
they flip and become left-handed can the
right-handed become a left-handed
left-handed become a right-handed yeah
that's exactly what the direct Theory
says but if it was moving with a speed
of light it couldn't why not because if
a thing is moving with a speed of light
time is infinitely slowed down and
nothing can happen to the object it just
moves along but nothing can happen
internally to the object so if its mass
was Zero it couldn't
flip but in the direct Theory this
flipping back and forth between I I tend
to do it this way but that's not right
this way this way this way this way that
is intimately associated with the mass
of the particle and in fact the mass of
a direct particle is simply proportional
to the rate at which it flips from left
to right that's the direct theory in a
nutshell mass is the rate for the
electron to flip back and forth from
left to
right okay of course the faster it's
going the slower it will flip but that's
all right you take that into account so
mass is left to right to left to right
and we could draw the motion of an
electron in the following way here's the
electron moving down the
axis at first it's right-handed so it's
going this way and then it's left-handed
it's going this way and then it's right
hand can you tell the difference maybe
not but that's okay and in
between it jumps from one to the
other the probability or the rate at
which it jumps is a measure of the mass
of the
electron so it jumps back and forth and
back and forth now I'm going to ask you
to believe something really crazy do you
remember this zebon where's the zosan
the zosan was
Associated was emitted it could be
emitted from electrons it could be
emitted from neutrinos but let's
concentrate on electrons it is not the
same as the
photon and the thing which emits it is
not the same as the electric charge it
is another kind of charge a completely
separate kind of charge it's like charge
but it emits Zebo we need a name for it
we don't have a name for it well we do
have a name for it's a very awkward name
it's called the weak hypercharge I don't
like that because it's the thing which
emits the Zebo zons I call it
zilch zilch zilch is like electric
charge but it's not electric charge when
a particle which has zilch accelerates
it emits a
zebon it may also emit a photon if it
also happens to have electric
charge now electrons both right-handed
and left-handed have the same electric
charge okay but left-handed and
right-handed electrons do not have the
same
Z in the standard model this is part of
the mathematics of the standard model
the the left-handed and the right-handed
electrons have different zilch the
left-handed electron has zilch of plus
one and the right-handed electron has
zero zilch I didn't make this up in fact
my friend Steve Weinberg didn't make it
up if anybody made it up he's up there
or down there I don't know where but uh
and uh it is just the way it is it is
the way the mathematics of the standard
model
works that the left-handed and the
right-handed particles have different
zil and now we have a
puzzle when the electron moves
along and it flips from left to right
that means the zilch goes from plus one
to zero but zilch is like electric
charge it's
conserved how can the zilch go from zero
to one it can't it can't and that's the
reason that the electron in the standard
model doesn't have a mass because the
left-handed and the right-handed have
different value of a conserved
quantity and so left can't go to right
period no Mass okay how do we get around
this we get around this by introducing a
new ingredient and the new ingredient is
called the zigs
bosan it's not the higs bosan not yet we
haven't gotten to the higsbo on yet
we've gotten to the zigs
boson the zigs Bon is one new
ingredient it
is closely connected with this Mexican
Hat type configuration
here it's a kind of
particle but it forms a
condensate you can't tell how many are
there you can put one in you can take
one out and so forth without changing
the
vacuum so we have one more ingredient
it's a condensate that space is filled
with and the nature of the condensate is
that doesn't have electric charge it has
zilch and it's a condensate meaning that
if you put a zilch in nothing happens if
you take one out nothing
happens and let's ask now what that
means the left-handed electron coming in
has a zilch of one let's call it a z of
one the right-handed has Z equal
Z back to the left-handed Z equal 1 is
that possible
only if you emit something at this point
which carries off that Z equals
1 a
zigs the zigs Bon gets
emitted it carries a z =
1 both what happens to
it where does it
go it goes into the
condensate it gets lost in the
condensate you put a you put one in and
it just gets absorbed into the
condensate and so the electron goes on
its merry way the condensate absorbs the
zilch and it goes from one to zero but
then it can borrow a particle back from
the condensate borrow one back it
doesn't even have to borrow it
if you pull one out nothing changes
again and so it goes on its merry way
from left-handed to right-handed from
left-handed to right-handed every time
it switches it emits a particle carrying
this zil quantum number which then just
gets absorbed into the
condensate that's the mechanism by which
a field and in this case it's a field
which forms a condensate by itself it
doesn't require capacitor plates it just
requires the energy to be such that the
field naturally gets
shifted and that's the mechanism by
which electrons quirks and the various
partners of those particles the me
particle the um too
lepton all those ordinary ordinary and
extraordinary particles the Fons get
their Mass by this phenomenon
here phenomenon doesn't really have a
name it's called the spontaneous
breaking of chyro symmetry but uh it
does have a name but this is what it is
okay what about the
zebon I told you before the zebon is
like a
photon photons are massless how does a
zebon get a mass so I'll just show you
something very similar happens to the
zeban let's remind ourselves what a
zosan can do it can take any particle
which has a zilch and in particular this
green zigs particle it can take the zigs
particle and the zigs particle can emit
a Zebo
on it has charge not real charge but
zilch and zilch emits
Zeos all right so now let's ask what
that means that means that a Zebo on
moving
along can do something a little bit
similar to this it
can
absorb some zilch out of the condensate
condensate but now it has zil originally
it was just a Zebo on zebon don't have
zilch it absorbs some zilch and it
becomes a zigs Zebo on becomes a zigs
but then it can emit the zigs which gets
lost in the condensate
again and the Zebo on just moves on its
merry way constantly going back and
forth from being
a Zebo on to being one of these
imaginary not imaginary uh zigs
particles that's the nature
of the way particles get Mass from
Fields this phenomenon of the zosan
getting a mass is called the brout
angare higs phenomenon this is the one
that's called the higs phenomenon the
zebon getting a mass now this could have
happened to the photon had there been a
condensate of ordinary charged particles
the photon would have become massive we
would all be dead if that were the case
massive photons would not be healthy for
us and so we are very lucky that uh that
this phenomenon here did not apply to
ordinary electric
charge will we ever discover the zigs
particle sure we discovered it long
ago it's just part of the zosan zosan
was discovered I mean was postulated
1967 but or even before that by many
people but it was discovered I don't
even remember around 1980 I forgot when
the uh when the experiment uh slack
first discovered the existence
experimentally but when it was
discovered that there was a Zebo on that
it had a mass and that when its
properties were studied the properties
were not only consistent but required
that it was a thing which went back and
forth and back and forth and back back
and forth between pure
zebon and the zigs particle so they've
existed we're not in doubt about them
and we never were at least not for many
years so far I have not mentioned the
higs
boson so what is the higs
boson well the higs boson has to do with
this condensate it has to do with this
condensate but it's a different kind of
exit ation than sliding around the uh
the edge of the sombrero here does not
have to
move it's not something which has to do
with sliding around here it has to do
I'll tell you two different ways to
think about it you have a condensate and
you can imagine the condensate has a
density a density of these uh fictitious
particles in the condensate imagine
something which changes the density of
them kind of like a sound wave a
compression wave of some kind which
squeezes them closer and further and
closer apart makes it more and more less
dense that kind of vibration is what a
higs higsbo on is another way to think
about
it is that it doesn't have to do with
sliding around the uh periphery of the
sombrero it's it go to a place in space
and start the field also ating this way
in and
out this way the further away it is the
stronger the condensate the closer to
the center the weaker the condensate so
when it soses back and forth It's Kind
of a compressional wave in the
condensate that
mode that phenomena that oscillation is
what is called a higs boson the Boon is
like the sound wave propagating through
the uh through the
condensate the reason it is been so
important is because it was the one
element that had not yet been
discovered as I said the zigs was
discovered long ago the Z and the W the
electrons and all the others were
discovered long ago and so the next
question which I'll try to answer in a
couple of in five minutes is why it was
so hard hard to discover the higs what
we discovered about it
and very very quickly what the future
might or might not bring try to do this
in a couple of
minutes okay
so what kind of thing does the higs BOS
on itself do now we're talking about the
higs BOS on not the zigs BOS on not the
zos on the higs itself the one the one
that's been so elusive all these years
it's called
H and what it can do with some
probability is for example create we
read this from left to right higs bosz
on moving along in time time is now to
the left can create an
electron and a
positron it can create a pair of
quirks it can also create other things a
me particle or a top Quark or a bottom
Quark all of the different
quarks electrons also neutrinos all the
various Fons can be created in pairs
when a higs boson decays you say if it's
like a sound wave why does it decay well
believe me sound waves Decay if they
didn't Decay you'd continue to hear my
voice ring forever and ever wouldn't you
so sound waves do
Decay and it is possible to think of
sound waves as decaying by creating
particles so the higs bosan decays it
decays quickly if it exists if it really
exists it decays quickly either into an
electron positron or a pair of quarks or
maybe some other of the Fons that exist
in nature you can read this diagram in
two different ways oh incidentally the
probability that the higs decays like
this is proportional to the mass of the
particle that it decays
into the the heavier the mass the more
strongly that particle is coupled to the
higs boson so heavy particles are
favored and light particles are not
favored now you can read this diagram in
either direction you can say the higs
boson decays but you can also say an
electron and a positron confused
together to make a higs
boson well if we want to make higs
bosons and see them in the laboratory we
want to read the diagram from right to
left and we want to say this is a
process whereby a pair of electrons can
come together and make a higs BOS
on we've been colliding electrons and
positrons for a long long
time almost as long as I've been a
physicist not quite we've been uh
colliding electrons and positrons
together and nobody was ever able to
discover the higs now one reason in the
early days is it turns out that the higs
is a fairly heavy particle I will tell
you what its masses but it's a fairly
heavy particle and unless you have
enough energy you don't have enough
energy to make the higs BOS on but
there's a more important reason in fact
slack in the later days of Slack's life
had plenty of energy to make the higs
the problem was the weakness of the
coupling the smallness of the mass of
the electron translated into a very weak
improbable
cross-section too small in effect too
unlikely to make the higs and so when
you Collide electrons together at high
energy electrons are just not favorable
they're too light and because they're
light they tend to not make higs with
any appreciable
probability well how about quirks we can
Collide quirks together
the usual quarks that make up the proton
and neutron are also very light and
because they are light also unlikely to
ever make a higs BOS on well you you I'm
sure they were made in slack but never
in appreciable numbers that it was
possible to uh toh detect them so that
was the main difficulty the lightness of
these particles was a thing that
essentially prohibited us from making
hig's in abundance at slack or in other
Laboratories where collisions took
place what is the most favorable
particle most likely
particle for the higs to decay in the
heaviest the heaviest of the Fons and
the heaviest of the firion is called the
top Quark the top Quark is hundreds and
hundreds thousands of times heavier than
the electron many thousand many many
times heav many thousands of times
heavier than the
electron and the higs preferentially
will Decay into top
quirks so we'll just call those the
quirks they are quirks but they're very
heavy 170 times the mass of a proton
basically which is heavy top and
anti-top top quirks and anti- quirks so
you say well look now it's easy to make
the higs bows on you just
oh actually in fact not possible for the
higs to Decay the two top quirks because
the two top quarks are too heavy but if
you read it the other way and you take a
pair of top quirks and Collide them
together you can make a higs so it's
easy we just go in the laboratory take a
pair of top quirks Collide them together
and make a higs well the problem is that
it's not so easy to find top quirks in
nature why not not they Decay very
rapidly to the other quirks they're not
sitting around you can't put them into
the accelerator and accelerate them they
disappear in a tiny fraction of a second
there are no top quirks sitting
around
uh not even buried inside protons and so
forth not even buried inside other kinds
of particles there are no top quarks
around so we have to make the top Quirk
somehow in the Collision how do you make
a top quk all right so here's a way to
make a top quk a gluon can come along
this is a gluon
now and remember what gluons do they
couple to
quirks one possibility is that the gluon
can make a top quark and an anti-top
Quark well there's plenty of gluons
around as we'll see in a
moment so why don't we just take a glue
on and make a top quk and an anti-top
Quark out of it the reason is because
gluons are very light they're almost
they're almost massless they don't weigh
very much top quirks are very heavy
there's simply not enough energy in the
gluon to create a pair of top quarks so
what we have to do is we have to take a
pair of gluons now here's a process that
you can imagine take a pair of gluons
with a lot of energy moving toward each
other with a huge speed plenty of energy
let one of them make a pair of top
quarks for a short period of time and
then let the other one come and be
absorbed by one of the top
quarks there we have it a pair of top
quarks created by a pair of gluons a
pair of high energy gluons smashed
together and make a pair of top
quirks once we've created those pair of
top quarks the top quarks can come
together and make our higs bow
on this is the way we usually draw this
is to just draw gluon gluon and then a
triangle higs these are top quirks going
around the loop here that's the most
efficient process for making um for
making higs bosons but where do you get
gluons from gluons aren't floating
around well yes they are the proton is
filled with gluons the
proton mass of the proton is maybe 50%
and energy from gluons or something like
that it's filled with gluons and
quirks you take two protons and you
Collide them together and the gluons
inside the protons can Collide during
the collision and do
this that was what was detected
at LHC LHC is a proton proton collider
it collides protons together and when
protons a very indirect way to prot
protons collide together a gluon from
each one of
them scatter Collide create a pair of
top quarks and then the top quarks then
have plenty
of come together and create the Hig BOS
on that's the process that was
discovered at the LHC and it took a long
time to get there it was a hard thing to
do it was a very very hard thing to do
but now it's done we know the mass of
the higs bosan it's 125 G about 127 time
the mass of the
proton and that's I think a finished
fact before I
quit Let's uh talk about the near
future what have we learned we've
learned that the standard model is
essentially correct we've learn the
standard model is essentially correct
everything seems to fit together the
higs bosz on fitting
together remember it's not the higs
boson really that gives the particles
their Mass it's the zigs boson but the
higs boson is just what's left over when
you think of these density oscillations
it was the last remaining piece it is
now in
place uh it's finished but is everything
fitting together exactly right
quantitatively right well that we don't
know we don't know there's one hint one
hint of a discrepancy and I'll tell you
what the hint of that discrepancy is
Let's uh here's I drew this picture let
me draw it again over
here it's the process
of creating a higs by two gluons coming
together gluon
gluon top Quark going around the loop
and
higs now this same process once the higs
is
created also allows the higs to decay
but it's not so easy to see gluons in
the laboratory they're difficult to work
with that's not the best process for
looking for the higs boson after you've
created it the best process is to
replace the gluons by photons I don't
have to even change the picture photons
it's exactly the same process except
with photons out here once the higs is
created by whatever it can create it it
can DEC K into two
photons it's an intricate process it
involves a lot of theory and a lot of
calculation a Fineman diagram not easy
to calculate but you can calculate it
and it depends on the properties of the
top Quirk going around here at the
moment at the moment and I'm not an
expert at this I can only quote what I'm
told a at the moment the higs bosan that
was produced in the laboratory appears
to Decay into two photons a little too
quickly about one and a half times too
quickly now everybody agrees that that
is not a statistically really
significant fact yet but what will it
mean if it persists it doesn't seem like
a big deal one and a half times too fast
but the point is the theorists have the
ability to calculate that rate very
accurately
a one and a half times too big a rate is
serious it means something is going on
the most likely thing that would be
going on is that there's another kind of
particle in addition to the top Quirk
that has not been discovered yet that
can also participate in the same kind of
it's called a triangle diagram some
other kind of particle that of course
would be big news if there's something
there that is not described by the
standard model that would be big news it
could be a super symmetric particle it
could be anything all kinds of things if
this this is something to watch for now
the buzzwords are the decay of the higs
into a pair of photons and a excess of
about one and a half I think it's a two
Sigma effect whatever that means means
something the
statisticians
um it means that it's not so robust but
it could be right right if it turns out
to be right it means that we've
discovered something
unexpected or it might be even something
that's expected but something new beyond
the standard model remember the standard
model is over 50 years old well over 50
years old and so 1967 am I right 77 87
2007 no not K getting on 50 years old so
discovering the hings bosone wasn't
really discovering anything was
confirming something if this should be
off by a factor of one and a half one
will have discovered something
absolutely new so if you want to watch
if you know want to be a spectator in
the sport and you want to watch what
happens this is the thing to watch for
next whether the higs
decays are consistent with the standard
model okay that's uh we we're finished
uh thank you very much and uh I hope you
all got something out of
that one or two questions
yeah uh what would cause two different
ferons to have different rat of chyro
oscillation
good the answer is going to be an
unsatisfying
one the answer
is that the Fons
have what would cause different Fons to
have different masses different masses
essentially different different
oscillation different rates of
oscillation are the same as different
masses the coupling strength the
coupling constant that
couples the relevant particle to the uh
to the higs
field what happens the particle
moves has separ coupl yes each one has a
separate coupling constant emits this
what did I call it the the zigs midst
the zigs which gets lost there's a
coefficient here which is basically a
probability
each one and we don't know why they are
what they are we know how to
parameterize it but we don't know how to
explain it for each kind of particle
let's say the electron or the MU
particle or whatever it happens to be
there's a different constant there and
that constant is the constant which
determines the rate and the mass it's
the same constant which comes
into telling you how rapidly the higs
decays into these particles and
therefore the the heavier the particle
the stronger the Decay so that's a good
question I meant to say something about
it I
forgot
good do we know the value of the H mask
do we know the value of the vacuum
expectation value of the H field yeah
we've known that for a long time 240 gev
the value of the expectation value is
from one language it's simply the
displacement of the field in another
language it's the density of the
condensate can think of it either way
the density of the condensate or as the
value of the displacement of the
field and that's why oscillation in the
magnitude of the field is the same as a
density
fluctuation what's
that apparently
not apparently not well yes I think it
does but there are many many other
things that give it an energy density
and for whatever reason they almost all
cancel out this is one of the great
mysteries of uh
you yeah right so that's that's a very
good question to which we don't have an
answer at the moment right okay I hope
you got something out of that I had fun
preparing it and figuring out how to try
to explain
it uh some of you you probably got
something others are just mystified and
sitting why they talking about but
that's it
[Applause]
for more please visit us at stanford.edu